<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aug. 7: 1670. A most useful sermon preached in London, By a most worthy and faithfhl [sic] minsiter and servant of Jesus Christs, most learnedly pressed from Amos 8. 11. ... From which text of scripture, he learnedly shews the dreadful and deplorable condition of that kingdom which a famine of the word of the Lord seizes upon; and further shews, that they are the greatest felons who would rob us of the word of God, and that there is more justice in hell then is here upon earth, for in hell they do not punnish the innocent</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2931BA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213887</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826143</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826143</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30535</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51487)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30535)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1798:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aug. 7: 1670. A most useful sermon preached in London, By a most worthy and faithfhl [sic] minsiter and servant of Jesus Christs, most learnedly pressed from Amos 8. 11. ... From which text of scripture, he learnedly shews the dreadful and deplorable condition of that kingdom which a famine of the word of the Lord seizes upon; and further shews, that they are the greatest felons who would rob us of the word of God, and that there is more justice in hell then is here upon earth, for in hell they do not punnish the innocent</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint place from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Amos VIII, 11 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Preaching --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30535:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30535:1"/>
            <p>Aug. 7: 1670. A moſt uſeful SERMON Preached in <hi>London,</hi> By a moſt worthy and faithful Miniſter and Servant of Jeſus Chriſts, moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly preſſed from <hi>Amos</hi> 8.11.</p>
            <q>Behold the day cometh, ſaith the Lord God, that I will ſend a famine in the Land, not a famine of bread, nor a thirſt for water, but of hearing the word of the Lord, and they ſhall wander from Sea to Sea</q>
            <p>From which Text of Scripture, he learnedly ſhews the dreadful and deplorable condition of that Kingdom which a famine of the word of the Lord ſeizes upon; and further ſhews, That they are the greateſt Felons who would rob us of the word of God, and that there is more juſtice in Hell then is here upon Earth, for in Hell they do not punniſh the Innocent.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1671.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:30535:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30535:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Amos 8.11.</bibl>
                  <p>Behold the day cometh, ſaith the Lord God, that I will ſend a Famine in the land, not a famine of Bread, nor a thirſt for Water, but of hearing the Word of the Lord; And they ſhall wander from Sea to Sea.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>A Sad Text, and Sad Times too well agree; In the beginning of this Chapter there is a Viſion, in the firſt verſe, The Lord hath ſhewed me, and behold a Basket of ſummer fruits, it was a Type or Embleme to ſignifie the ſuddainneſs of <hi>Iſraels</hi> miſery; you know ſummer fruit doth ſoon periſh, winter fruit may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved long, but ſummer fruit doth ſoon fade; ſo the glory of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (like to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer fruit) it ſhall ſoon fade away; there is the Viſion.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:30535:3"/>
            <p n="2">2. In this Chapter there is a Propheſie in the 32<hi>d</hi> verſe; The Songs of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſhall be turned into howling, a ſad Propheſie, God grant it may not be our Portion; ſongs of the Temple to become howling, where God formerly was ſerved in a pure manner, where there was ſweet ſinging and melody unto the Lord, now there would be mournful Songs, that joy of the Temple it ſhall be quite ceaſed; A ſad Propheſie!</p>
            <p n="3">3. In this Chapter is ſet down the cauſe why the Lord did write ſuch bitter things againſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> his own People, the cauſe was very apparent; it was their ſin, ſin drew Plagues at the heels of it, <hi>Iſrael</hi> grew now weary of God in the 5<hi>th</hi> verſe of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, When will the New Moon be gone, that we may ſell corn, they had rather a great deal be trading in their ſhops, then worſhiping in Gods houſe; when will the New Moon be gone, when people grow weary of Ordinances, then God grows weary of a People. And</p>
            <p n="4">4. There are ſet down the puniſhments for thoſe ſins of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the 9<hi>th</hi> verſe of this Chapter, I will cauſe the Sun to go down at Noon day. Beloved this is not meant the natural Ecline of the Sun, but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30535:3"/> the meaning is, God would now darken <hi>Iſraels</hi> outward glory and ſplendor; The Sun in Scripture is a Metaphor for joy; now the going down of the Sun at noon, it is to expreſs great afflictions coming upon this People: when they thought all things ſhould be well, every thing ſhould be well, flouriſhing peace and proſperity, kiſſing each other, why now there ſhould be a ſuddain change, God would Eclipſe their outward Comforts; ſaith he, the Sun ſhall go down at Noon day, and this was not all, there is a greater puniſhment yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and that is, in the Text I have read. God threatens for their ſins, that there ſhould be a Famine in the Land, not a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of Bread, nor a Thirſt for Water, but of hearing the Word of the Lord, (as if God ſhould ſay) it was a mercy if onely a Famine upon your Bodies, that may pine your Bodies, Oh, but it is a worſe, a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Famine; a Famine of hearing the Word of the Lord. In which Text, you have theſe four parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is a note of admiration in theſe words, Behold it ſeems to be a wonder, that <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God's People in Covenant, to whom the Oracles of God were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that theſe ſhould want the word of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30535:4"/> Lord: Oh what a wonder that ſuch a full breaſt ſhould be drawn dry! that they that had ſuch plenty of Ordinances, ſhould now be cut ſhort, and forced to cry out, We ſee not our ſigns, there is no more any Prophet among us, that's the firſt. Behold there is admiration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is the judgment threatned in the Text, a ſoul Famine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The extention and univerſality of this Famine, why ſaith God, it ſhall be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in the Land, not in a Houſe or Pariſh, but there ſhall be this ſoul Famine, it ſhall be univerſal in the Land.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Who it is that gives the Famine a Commiſſion, and that is God; I will ſend a Famine, not of Bread, or Water, but of hearing of the Word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The words thus opened into theſe ſeveral parts, they yeild us theſe four Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Doctrines.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It doth ſhew, That the word of God is to the ſoul as food to the body, for ſtrengthning and refreſhing of it, and that's imply'd in <hi>Job</hi> 23.12. I eſteemed the words of thy mouth, as my neceſſary food, they are my food that my ſoul feeds upon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond Doctrine is this, When the word of God is deſpiſed or oppoſed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30535:4"/> it is juſt with the Lord to take it away from a People.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third Doctrine is this, The taking away of the word, is the beginning of a Spiritual famine, and</p>
            <p n="4">4. That a famine of the word, is far worſe then a famine of Bread. A famine I will ſend, ſaith God, not of Bread, nor of Thirſt for Water, but which is worſe, the hearing of the word of the Lord. The famine of the word is worſe then a famine of bread; next to damning of a ſoul, what can be worſe then ſtarving of it; bodily famine is very ſad, much more ſpiritual fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. I ſhall ſpeak a little of bodily famine, that will ſet off the other the more.</p>
            <p>Famine is that with-drawing of an ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary recruit of Nature, Famine is the with-holding of that Oyle which ſhould be poured into the Lamp of Man's Life; Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and Death is ſuch as you ſee a picture, they both bring the Body into an Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: See a deſcription of a famine in <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.3. Their Nobles have ſent their little ones to the water, they came to the pit and found no water, they were aſhamed and confounded, and covered their heads. It is a very unuſual ſight to ſee Noble Mens Children Tanckard-bearers; the Nobles
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30535:5"/> ſent their Children, but found no water, Famine of the Body is worſe than the Sword is, and that in theſe three reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Sword cuts off ſuddainly, it makes a quick diſpatch, now Famine makes you dye a lingring death, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.9. Thoſe pine away, ſtrucken through for want of the fruit of the field; they pine away. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine will neither let a man live, nor yet ſuffer him to dye. He that is in famine, may ſay as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> In death oft, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deaths doth he dye, before he dyes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Famine is univerſal, it reaches more then the Sword, the Sword skips over ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; they may be hid from the edge of the Sword, as we read of <hi>Obadiah,</hi> he hid a Thouſand Prophets in a Cave, and ſo eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the edge of the Sword, now a Famine reaches all.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Famine makes a man cruel to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and it is like a Wolfe in his breaſt, it makes a man feed upon himſelf; he eats the fleſh of his own arms; it makes a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon unnatural, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.10. Thus the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of the Body is worſe than the Sword, and now Beloved, a Famine of the Word is worſe than a Famine of Bread, in theſe two reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Famine of Bread is onely a pineing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30535:5"/> and ſtarving of the body, Oh, but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſtarving of the ſoul; by how much more pretious the ſoul is then the body, ſo much the ſadder the famine of the ſoul muſt needs be; the ſoul is the moſt ſpiritual and reſerved part of man; it's like ſpirits of wine; the ſoul is a divine ſpark that flees upwards towards God. Now if the ſoul be more noble than the body, then the famine of the ſoul muſt needs be more deadly and pernitious than that of the Body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Famine of the body is but tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, but for a time, and it will quickly have an end, ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 35. Oh, but the Famine of the ſoul is eternal. The worm will be ever gnawing the man; the man will be ever dying, but never dead; he will never taſt of one drop of the water of life, it is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal famine, he ſhall not have one drop of water to cool his tongue, and thus you ſee the Famine of the word is far more grievous than the Famine of bread: Now the ſadneſs of the ſouls famine, will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appear in theſe three or four particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; And I beſeech you obſerve.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To have the Famine of the Word of God, it is a dreadful Judgement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe now the very means of Salvation is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30535:6"/> taken away: The very Bridge is plucked up, that ſhould lead us over to Heaven. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.18. <hi>Where there is no Viſion the people periſh.</hi> The <hi>Hebrew</hi> word for <hi>periſh,</hi> hath two ſignifications, either it ſignifies to be made naked, <hi>they. ſtrip off their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments and glory,</hi> or elſe the word <hi>periſh,</hi> ſignifies to reject, God rejects ſuch a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when he takes awy the <hi>Viſion</hi> from them, <hi>Where there is no Viſion the people periſh.</hi> But now here is a Queſtion may be asked,</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> You will ſay unto me, but may we not be ſaved without the Word Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> I will not diſpute what God can do, in an extraordinary way, when peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are debarr'd from Ordinances by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or the like, or captivity, the Lord hath promiſed to be a little Sanctuary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.16. As the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> when they could not have the ordinary means of tilling, plowing, and ſowing; in this caſe God gave them bread from Heaven, <hi>John</hi> 6.31 Let me aſſure you, ordinarily God doth not diſtil the Golden Oyle of Salvation, but through the pipes of Ordinances, and therefore you ſhall obſerve in Scripture,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30535:6"/> that Miniſters of the Goſpel, are called Miniſters of the Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8. becauſe the ſpirit of God ordinarily makes uſe of the Word, to work grace, and therefore 'tis called the Miniſtry of the ſpirit, why this makes the Famine of the Word ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, becauſe now, the very means of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is taken away from a people, they lie in their blood.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I beſeech you obſerve, A Famine of the Word it is very ſad wherever it comes, becauſe now the Lord turns away his face from a people or a nation. Ordinances are the face of God, they are his ſmiles, face, in the Goſpel, it's called the face of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 4.6. Now beloved, when a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Famine comes, God turns away his face from us. The Child had rather have his Fathers frowns upon him, than that he ſhould turn away his face, to be ſo incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt him that he will not look upon his Child; and this is ſad, to have God turn away his face from a people; better have a frowning face from God, than noe face. The Lord may have love under a wrinckled brow, as the ſun may be under a Clowd; but for God to turn away his face from us, is a ſigne he intends to diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit us, as <hi>David</hi> prayed, <hi>Lord hide not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30535:7"/> thy face from me in Anger, Pſal.</hi> 120.2. It is ſad when God hides his face for a time, but worſe when he quite turns away his face, that he will not look upon a people, Oh this makes a ſoul-famine very ſad and dreadful.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Famine of the Word muſt needs be very ſad and diſmal, becauſe if the Word be gone, God has now done ſpeaking to us, he hath no more to ſay. Pray obſerve, It is called in the Text a famine of hearing, of hearing of the Word, we ſhall hear no more from God; God hath ſomething to ſay to a people as long as his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are amongſt them; he ſpeaks to them by his Miniſters, they are his mouth, they deliver his Council. Now as it is a ſad judgement for God to have done ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a people, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.5. why ſhould you be ſmitten any more, and ſo for God to leave ſpeaking to a people, this is a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious people, it is to no purpoſe to uſe any more words, I will ſpeak no more to them, it is better for God to ſpeak as if he were angry, than not to ſpeak at all: the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner cryes to his Judge for mercy, mercy, and the Judge will not ſpeak a word noe way, but he muſt dye; if God hath done ſpeaking to us in Word, we ſhall hear him
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30535:7"/> ſpeaking in another Language, in his Wrath, In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.5. <hi>then ſhall he ſpeak to them in his Wrath, and fiery Language.</hi> If a man will not ſpeak to another, it is a ſign either that he ſlights him, or he doth not think him worth ſpeaking to, or it is ſign he intends ſome evil againſt him. It was ſad with <hi>Saul</hi> when the Lord had done ſpeaking to him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.6. the Lord anſwered him nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by rain, nor his Prophets, God had done ſpeaking to him, a ſign ſome evil was intended to him, the next be heard ſpeak, it was the Devil, and the news which he brought was ſad, to morrow thou ſhalt be with me, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.19. beloved if God hath once done ſpeaking to a people, why then he hath done hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing to when he ſhuts his mouth he alwayes ſtops his ears, though you pray unto him he will not hear; <hi>they cryed to me and</hi> I <hi>would not hear;</hi> when the Lord will not ſpeak no more to a people, when he ſhuts his mouth, he preſently ſtops his ears: Now is not a ſpiritual fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſad? God hath now done ſpeaking to a people.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The people and the diſpenſers of the Goſpel, they are promiſed by the Lord as great bleſſings to a place, why then to be deprived of ſuch bleſſings, and have a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30535:8"/> of the Word it muſt needs be a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and a diſmal Judgement. Now to ſpeak more diſtinctly to theſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider what a great bleſſing the Goſpel is, and</p>
            <p n="2">2. The diſpenſers of it, and then you will eaſily conclude what a Judgement it is to be deprived of them.</p>
            <p>As for the Goſpel, it is a bleſſing which Crowns a people, the very Engine which God uſes to convert a Soul. It is called in Scripture the word of life, becauſe it enfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes life into the people, it is a two edged ſword, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. with one edge it ſtrikes ſin dead, with the other edge it ſtrikes the ſoul alive. beſides conſider the great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of this people in theſe three particulars, and you will ſee what it is to be deprived, of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Goſpel of Chriſt, it is the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the riches, it is the ſtrength of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the moſt ſparkling Jewel in their Crown, the beauty of God ſhines in the Goſpel, Brethren, the Goſpel is the glaſſe in which we ſee, the unſearchable riches of Gods love to a ſinner. The Goſpel preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed gives us the preſence of Chriſt, and Chriſts preſence is the ſpiritual beauty of a Nation; now if there be a famine of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30535:8"/> the Word, then the glory is departed. <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> without the Goſpel will be like unto a houſe, when the rich furniture and hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are pulled down, the houſe is naked and deformed; ſo if the preaching of the Word be Eclipſed, then the glory of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is Entombed, and all places of honour lye in the duſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The preaching of the Goſpel is the riches of a Kingdome, it encreaſes a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms treaſure and revenue; there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny temporal bleſſings that come along with the word, it hath been obſerved that thoſe places have been moſt fruitful and have been moſt enriched where the Goſpel hath been planted, trading in thoſe parts hath been moſt quick; it is obſervable that ſame place of King <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> that when he had taken care for a preaching Miniſtry, and ſent his Princes and his Nobles to encourage his Miniſters; Oh how rich did his kingdome grow, they brought him preſents of ſilver, and he waxed exceeding rich, 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 17.11. The Goſpel it is like the Ark which carries a bleſſing with it where ever it went, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.18. ſaith God, Conſider from this day, even from the day that the Lords Temple was laid, from this day will I bleſſe you: <hi>Iſraels</hi> mercies did bear date
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30535:9"/> from the Temple building; ſo that the Goſpel is the riches of a Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Mark what I ſay to you this day, the ready way to beggar a Kingdom is to take away the Goſpel: I beſeech you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a Famine of Gods word will ſoon bring a Famine of Bread upon a Land.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Goſpel preached is the defence of a Kingdom, it is a Kingdoms ſafely and defence, it is the Fort-Royal of a Land, it is the very lock where on <hi>Englands</hi> ſtrength lies; what was the ſtrength of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God was there, there was his word, and there was his ordinances, that was the Rock where <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſtrength did lye, not brazen Walls but ſilver Trumpet are the beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our Land. It is ſaid of the <hi>Levites</hi> or Miniſters, that when they came &amp; preached at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.17. The Text ſaith, thry ſtrengthened the Kingdom. It is remarkable in Scripture, they as take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the preaching of the Goſpel, are like thoſe that pull down the Bancks to let in the main Sea, they open a ſluce to let in the wrath of God upon a Kingdom; thus you ſee the Goſpel is a ſingular bleſſing, and therefore to have a famine of the word, to have the Goſpel go, it muſt needs be a great curſe to a Land.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:30535:9"/>
            <p>Again, as the Goſpel is a great bleſſing ſo the Diſpenſers, the Miniſters of the word, they are promiſed as great bleſſings to a Land; and therefore to have them remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and a Soul famine, it is a heavy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: God promiſes his Miniſters as bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to a Nation; <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.15. I will give you Paſtors after mine own heart, that ſhall feed you with knowledge, and that they are great bleſſings, appears by the title the Scripture gives to them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are called the Diſpenſers and Stewards of Gods word, they are called Embaſſadours, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. We as Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of God, beſeech you in Chriſts ſtead to be reconciled, we come to wo you in Chriſts name, and clear up your ſouls to Chriſt, we come to make up the happy match between Chriſt and you, we bring the Kings picture along with us, we ſet before your eyes the Lord Jeſus in his moſt Orient Colours, we ſhow him to you in the beauty of his Perſon, the glory of his Offices, the ſweetneſs of his love; why now, if on a ſuddain God calls home his Embaſſadours, it is a ſign he intends the match ſhall be broken off.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are called Diſpenſers and Stewards of the word of God, they are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30535:10"/> called ſtars in Gods hand, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20. They are ſtars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For their light, how glorious is the Goſpel when it is beſpangled and ſet thick with thoſe ſtars.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they are ſtars not only for light but for uſe, they are like the ſtar that guided the wiſe man to Jeſus Chriſt, if thoſe ſpiritual ſtars be removed, how ſhall the ſoul know how to ſteer its courſe, they will be like Mariners that are benighted upon Shelves and Rocks, Oh, how many where theſe ſtars are wanting, ſhall to hell in the Dark.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are called Diſpenſers and Stewards of Gods holy Oracles. They are called Phyſitians, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.22. Is there no Balm in <hi>Gilead,</hi> is there no Phyſitian there! the ſoul of man is ſubject to more Diſeaſes then the Body, as one Chriſtian is troubled with the Stone of the heart, another with a dead Palſey; and benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of Conſcience, now it is the work of Gods Miniſters to find out theſe Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and to apply proper remedy. Beloved how ſad is it, to have your Phyſitian taken away that ſhould heal you, to have a poor ſoul lie all in Agony, in a burning Feavour of Conſcience, and now to ſpeak words in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30535:10"/> due ſeaſon, or drop in Chriſt, is there no Balm in <hi>Gilead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. God calls his Miniſters his Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Apollo's</hi> was a Waterer, now you know if you have a plant ſet in a good ſoil, if it be not watered, it yields no fruit. This City of <hi>London</hi> hath had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Apolloes</hi> in it, it hath had much wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, you have been watered with the Labourers of your Miniſters, and perhaps watered with their Tears too; Oh, but for your ſins, God may command, that there ſhall be no more ſhowers, no more watering; If the Lord ſhould tranſplant his <hi>Apolloes,</hi> and ſee there is more need of watering and planting in forreigne parts, how would this work of Grace go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in us, how would your good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wither, and be as the ground that is parched and dryed for want of ſhowers; Thus Beloved, you ſee what a great bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is to have the Goſpel Diſpenſers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, and therefore you may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine what a ſpiritual famine is, and to have theſe bleſſings removed; well may <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> weep her eyes out, when theſe are gone that ſhould bring the Viſion to her.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:30535:11"/>
            <p>Now my Beloved, if a famine of Gods word be ſo deplorable and dreadful as it is to have the Bread of life taken away from us, as you may read <hi>Amos</hi> 8.11. It is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there, A famine of the word of the Lord, and in <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.4. it is called there, The glory departed, and in <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.47. The Kingdome of Heaven taken away, The Salvation of God ſent away, <hi>Acts</hi> 28. and can there be any thing worſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall a people, than a ſoul famine, and an Eclipſe of their ſpiritual glory, the ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of the Kingdome of heaven, the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying away of the Salvation of God, what worſe thing can come upon a people? It is a great wonder there ſhould be no deeper a ſence of this moſt dreadful of evils, than is moſtly found among Men. Men little underſtand what they do, who either in a way of Merit, or Inſtrumentally procure and bring on theſe Plagues, and few under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand or are ſenſible what they herein ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; to be an inſtrument in this helliſh work, it's an Office for a Devil; and the ſuffering of ſuch a Plague to them as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, is an hell above ground; this Darkneſs is the very ſame for kind, with the darkneſs of Hell, as the light of the Goſpel is the ſame in kind with the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30535:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> everlaſting light, as glory under age; ſo is this thick darkneſſe, <hi>in ſpecei &amp; in ſimile,</hi> the darkneſſe of the pit, Oh what a hell of wickedneſſe doth this world then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, the Devil is then in his Region, is let looſe and rules the world at pleaſure, deceives, devours, deſtroys ſouls without Contradiction, takes them Captive at his will, carries them down by whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale to diſtruction. Theſe dark, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal ſeaſons are the Devils Marker, where he may vent his helliſh Wares, his Snares and Temptations, his Deceipts and Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and every abominable thing by whole-ſale; there is nothing ſo falſe, ſo vile and abominable, but he can put it off at pleaſure, Adultery, Drunkenneſſe, Witchcraft, Sodomy, Buggery, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, Idolatry, Atheiſme, any thing that Sathan hath to offer he will find Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers enough to receive, and the truth is, the Devil may ſpare his pains; Men then need not a Devil to damne them, they ſhall do it faſt enough of their own Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords.</p>
            <p>Oh, it were happy if the Saints were ſo buſie in improving their light, to haſte them Heaven-ward, as ſinners do their larkneſſe, to hurry them to Hell.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:30535:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Oh, the ſad truths that the world af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords of this dreadful truth; look into all the dark Corners of the Earth, eſpecially there where there hath been light, and ſee if you find not all this proved to your hand. Can he then be accounted a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian whoſe heart doth not tremble at the thoughts and the fears of ſuch a ſore judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he is both dark and dead indeed, to whom ſuch a Miſt is not as the firſt born of death, or the King of Terrours.</p>
            <p>Chriſtians, If ever this ſhould be your Caſe, make not light of it, and take heed, how ſad ſoever it may ſeem in its firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, that no track of time do wear off the ſence of it; I have now done, and come to improve this Propoſition, and proceed to the Application.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1.</label> Now my friends, If a famine of the word be ſo dreadful (as you have heard) next to damning of ſouls, I know not what worſe then ſtarving of a ſoul, if it be ſo diſmal, then what are we to think of thoſe that endeavour by their Counſel and by their Intereſt, what in them lies, to be inſtrumental to bring a famine of the word upon Gods People.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30535:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> For my part I account thoſe, and always ſhall do, the greateſt Felons in the Land, who would rob us of the word of God; theſe are the Devils Agents, they are his Factors; let me aſſure you they will be found fighters againſt God; They are like the <hi>Philiſtians</hi> that ſtops the Wells (thoſe that would ſtop the Wells of the Water of Life) Oh, how would this inhaunce their ſin! What to be inſtrumental to ſtarve ſouls? I will ſay but this, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Jeſus Chriſt they are to warn people of their Sins, they are to tell them if there be any danger, any wrath of God hanging over a Land, they are Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.6.2. If Watch-men ſee the Sword come and blow not the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and the People be not warned; their blood I will require at the Watch-mens hands. Now Bretheren I appeal to you; We Watch-men muſt warn the people. Oh how will they be able to anſwer to God at the great day, that ſhall take Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters off from his Spiritual Watch, that ſhall hinder him from warning the People; Surely the blood of ſouls muſt needs lie at thoſe mens doors; that is the Firſt.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:30535:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2.</label> It is of Exhortation, if a Goſpel Famine be ſo dreadful as you have heard, as good almoſt be in hell; why then let me exhort you this day to ſome duty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us labour with all laboriouſneſs to prevent the removal of the Goſpel from us, as we would endeavour to remove the Sword, the Fire, the Plague, ſo let us la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to prevent the removal of the Goſpel from us: Oh a Goſpel famine is the moſt diſmal! and the more let my words prevail with you, becauſe there is ſo much fear (if God prevent not) of the Goſpel departing from us. I might ſhew you that there is a ſoul famine in many parts of this Land alreadie, and there are many ſad ſigns, the Lord is about to bring this ſpiritual famine upon this Land. I ſhall ſhew you the ſad ſimptoms of the Goſpel going from <hi>England,</hi> there are (4. gray haires) 4. ſad ſignes of the Goſpel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, which the Lord prevent.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt of all that great contempt which is thrown upon the Goſpel and profeſſors of it; do we think that God is tied to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30535:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>England</hi> more than to another Nation? do we think the Lord will continue his mercie to a people that diſpiſe his mercie? is he bound to do that? is nor the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus this day ſlighted and perſecuted? the <hi>Gergeſens,</hi> they were more mannerly, they beſeeched Chriſt to depart out of their Coaſts <hi>Matt.</hi> 8.3. But we have many among us, they do not beſeech Chriſt, they would drive him out by force, though nothing but hony dropps from the Lipps of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, it brings ſalvation to a people, yet how is it oppoſed at this day? pray ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, I confeſs the Goſpel of Chriſt, it is not ſuited to mens carnal intereſt or appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, the Goſpel doth not tell them of Fields and Vineyeards it hath to beſtow upon them, the Goſpel of Chriſt doth not propheſie of Wine and ſtrong Drink, then the Drunkard would gladly receive the Goſpel; but it is a holy Goſpel, it bears down mens luſts, it proclaimes peace to them upon no other tearms, but their proclaiming Warre againſt Sinne, and therefore the Goſpel is hated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, and ſurely this contempt of Chriſt and his Goſpel, it is a ſad fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30535:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the removal of the Goſpel: Marke what I ſay, a deſpiſed Goſpel will ſoone be a departing Goſpel; will any man ſtay long in a place where he is not welcome? If God ſees that he and his Goſpel are not welcome, he will ſoon take his leave and be gone from them <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Woe, Woe to them when I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from them.</hi> Well, that is the firſt ſad ſimptom of the Goſpel departing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Another ſign of the goſpel going, it is the general barrenneſſe of people under the preaching of the goſpel; indeed it is to be hoped that ſome are fruitful, but the barren branches are more than the fruitful; <hi>Lea</hi> did comfort her ſelf for her fruitfulneſs that now her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band would love her, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.34. <hi>She was fruitful, therefore her Husband would love her.</hi> May not we on the contrary fear God will not love us becauſe we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful? it is a ſad ſign, when in the Weekly bill we ſee more every Weeke die than are born; Oh is it not ſo in a ſpiritual ſence? we hear of many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that die Apoſtates, but how few are born to God. We hear of many barren Fig-trees that Chriſt curſed, but where
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30535:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> are the fruitful Vines? if once that goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; and people which was as the garden of God, ſhall become barren, it is a ſign the Lord will beſtow no more coſt, but will pull up the hedge, and lay his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard waſte; that is the ſecond Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. Another ſad ſign of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel going from us, which the Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, it is the animoſſities and bitter divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Gods own people; the Devil danceth at diſcords, it is a ſad ſight not onely to ſee Chriſts Coat rent, but to ſee his Bodie rent, his miſtical Bodie. I have often ſeen, &amp; it is uſual, the Woolf to worrie the Lamb, but it is unnatural to ſee one Lamb worrying another: Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, they ſhould be ready to dye one for another, and they can hardly live one by another: Thoſe that write con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Bee, obſerves, when the Bees ſtrive and mutanie together, it is a ſigne that the maſter Bee is about to leave the Hive; and when Gods people ſtrive by diſcords &amp; contentions, Oh it is a ſign God is goi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> from the Nation, he is about; to leave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ive. If that ſervants cannot
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30535:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> agree, they will fall out, why the Maſter will take away the light from them, I wiſh it be not ſoe here. My be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, do not we all hope for one hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? Oh why ſhould there not be one heart among us? how unſationable are contentions among Gods people, now when the Popiſh adverſary is ſo near to us, he is at the door. It is a very bad time for Marriners to divide and fall out when the Enemie is boreing a hole a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the bottom of the ſhip; is it not ſo now? ſurely it is a ſad ſigne of the goſpel going from us, the Lord will not let his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel dwell in ſuch a houſe as is all on fire.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Another ſad ſigne of the Goſpel going from us and a Spiritual Famine, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is this; When the People of God loſe their firſt love, and decline in their affections towards Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4. I have ſomewhat againſt thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt left thy firſt love; when Chriſtians have a Chilneſſe and a Dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe grow upon them, they have not the love to the word of God as they had, they have not that brokenneſs of heart for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30535:15"/> ſin, they have not that zeal for truth, they have not that ſimpathize for the miſery of <hi>Sion,</hi> they are now in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining ſtate, they have left their firſt love, and this is a fatal ſigne of Gods departing from the Nation; Loſt thy firſt love, it will not be amiſs to enquire whence this loſſe of our firſt love ariſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; this Spiritual Conſumption (as I may ſo call it,) whence does this loſs of our love ariſe, I conceive it ariſeth from theſe four Cauſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Perhaps there is ſome ſin ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indulged, ſome ſinne that your heart ſets brooding upon, now ſinne is perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to grace; it is like the blow at the Root of the Tree, that cauſeth the Tree to wither; as if a man takes but a ſmall quantity of poiſon, why this will hurt his virals, it will waſte his ſpirit, look upon <hi>David,</hi> he had been taking of poiſon, he was tampering with ſin and he found a decay in his holineſs, he was like one in an Apoplexſie, he had not that live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acting of Grace as formerly he had, he loſt his firſt love.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:30535:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Secondly, The loſſe of our firſt love, it may ariſe from the neglecting of the Ordinances, the means of Grace; you know abſtinaſie from food will quickly make the body Conſumptive, it will ſoon bring a Conſumption; ſo when People either through Pride or through Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly leave off Praying, leave off Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; they have abſtinaſie from their Spiritual food, no wonder if they find a declining in their affections; Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances they are the fuel for our Graces, if you take away the fuel, no wonder you begin to abate and you looſe your firſt love.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The loſſe of our firſt love ariſeth, and I pray obſerve it, it riſeth from a formal uſe of holy things; though perhaps we do keep up duty, yet God knows we do not keep up fervency in duty, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11. Fervent in ſpirit ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Lord. Oh, when once Chriſtians grow into dull formality, pray as if they prayed not, their hearts is not in the duty, they do not put ſire to the inſence, they grow Drowſie in Prayer, you know the wiſe Virgins they ſlumbered, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30535:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> Thus by degrees you loſe your firſt love, though you be not quite dead in ſin, yet you are dead in duty.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The loſs of your firſt love, ariſeth from a ſpiritual ſloath, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do not exerciſe themſelves to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and then there follows a decay in godlineſs; why, you know your expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience tells you there is nothing in the world ſooner brings a mans body into a Conſumption than want of exerciſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ill humours are not purg'd away, and natural heat exerciſed, want of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe kills. My brethren, he that will not uſe grace, he will be ſure to looſe grace; Chriſtians they do not exerciſe their faith, they do not buſie themſelves about hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, they do not trade their Tallent for Gods glory as they ſhould; they live in houſes together, but they do no good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they do not exerciſe their grace, and hence they fall into decay of grace before they are aware and looſe their firſt love, and what follows, this loſs of your firſt love ſadly prefages the loſs of the goſpel of Chriſt, for this very ſin in the ſecond of the <hi>Revelations</hi> and the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30535:17"/> 4<hi>th v.</hi> for ſin they had their golden Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſtick removed from them, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of the <hi>Revelations</hi> and the firſt verſe. Therefore you ſee brethren what need there is to labour to prevent the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Famine, and a loſs of the goſpel, becauſe there is ſuch a fear of the goſpel departing from your; you have ſeen it evidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before your eyes.</p>
            <p>But here is a queſtion; now you will ſay unto me, we cannot denie but there is a fear of the removal of the goſpel, and of a famine of the Word; but how ſhall we do to prevent this ſoul Famine? now to this I anſwer, do theſe three or four things to prevent the goſpel going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Take heed of thoſe ſins which will ſurely bring a Famine of Gods Word, there are ſome ſinnes which we muſt endeavour to prevent, that will bring a famine of the word, there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of theſe ſinnes ſet down in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Amos</hi> 8. Pray obſerve them. I will mention ſome of them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30535:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30535:18"/>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:30535:18"/>
            <p>The firſt ſinne the Prophet does ſet down, is Oppreſſion, <hi>Amos</hi> 8.11. Hear this, Oh you that ſwallow up the needy. Thoſe Jews they were like the Fiſhes of the Sea, the greater devour the leſſer; For this ſin of Oppreſſion God threatens a Famine of the Word, and is not this ſinne to be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us. Oppreſſion, I appeal to any one that hath his Reaſon left. Does not one Man now become a Woolfe to another, does not he tear from him the Golden Fleece; I dare be bold to ſay there is more Juſtice to be found in Hell then among men upon Earth; for in Hell no Innocent Perſon is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, that is one ſinne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Another ſinne the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſets down, that is the cauſe of this Spiritual Famine; it was wearineſſe of Gods Ordinances, <hi>Amos</hi> the 5<hi>th</hi> and 8<hi>th</hi> Verſe. When will your New Moons be gone that we may ſell Corne, and the Sabbath that we may ſet forth Wheat, Verſe 6. For this ſinne I will bring a Famine of the Word; are you
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30535:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> weary of me, They were more for Trading then they were for worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; The Lord hath fed us of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the fineſt of the Wheat, the Bread of life, he hath given us the very Creame of his Ordinances, but when we have been fed to the full, have not we begun to ſurfeit, have we not ſaid, when will the Sabbath be gone, what a wearineſſe is it? Truely when we have loſt our Stomach, it is moſt juſt with God to take away our Food; If a Mans Commodities bares a better price in one place then in another, he will remove his Marker; the Goſpel is grown a cheap Commodity, it bears but a loe price; now Men are weary of it: and may not we fear God will remove his Market, he will tranſplant his Word into Foreign parts: Surely if we begin to ſay what a wearineſs is it if our mercies be our burthens, God can ſoon eaſe us of this burthen; this is a ſinne brings a Famine of the Word, when we are weary of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; and hath not this ſinne cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Famine of the Word already in many parts of this Land. There is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30535:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> none knows how to ſpeak to their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Caſe, that can feed them with the Bread of life, that can divide the Word aright, in many parts of the Land it is ſo, they have Husks given to them inſtead of Food, and Muſick inſtead of Manna.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Another ſinne that brings a ſoul Famine, is this cozening in mens Dealings, Verſe 5. Making the Ephar ſmall, the Ephar it was the Kings Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Verſe 7. In ſelling they made the Ephar ſmall, the meaning is, they gave but ſcanty Meaſure; they made the Ephar ſmall; and ſaith God, you ſell the refuge of the Wheat, that is mear Cheating, they pick out of the beſt Grain for themſelves, and the Husks and Refuge they ſell to the poor; here is mear Cheating, ſaith God, I will bring a Famine of the Word up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you for this; let none hold in their hands falſe Ballances: I would there did not.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:30535:20"/>
            <p>Fourthly, Another ſinne that brings a Famine in this Chapter, is Idolatry, Verſe 4. They that ſwear by the ſinne of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and ſay, Thy God Oh <hi>Dan</hi> liveth, here was plain Idolatry; but let us underſtand this ſinne of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> what was that? that was the Calf that was ſet up at <hi>Bethel</hi> near to <hi>Samaria,</hi> and to ſwear to this Calf, here was plain Idolatry; for this God threatned a Famine of the Word, and are we free from this ſinne, I would we were: is there no Idol worſhip a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, are there not ſome ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, as to ſay in Print, It will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be well with us till we are recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to the Mother Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> Idolatry it inrageth God, it breaks the Marriage Knot, it makes God give a Bill of Diſvorce to a People; Idolatry it does ſo provoke the Lord, that he takes away the viſible Tokens of his preſence from a Nation, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.12.18. they ſerved Idols, What fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, Verſe 18. Therefore the Lord was very angry with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> removed them quite out of his ſight, he unpeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled them, he unchurched them, he
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30535:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> removed them out of his ſight. I ſay this to you, when once you ſee darke ſhaddows of Popery ſtretched out, then fear the Sunne of the Goſpel is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Another ſinne that brings a Goſpel Famine, it is oppoſition to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, when God calls to a Land to returne to him by Repentance, <hi>Turn ye, turn ye, why will you die?</hi> but they will go on in ſinne when God cries to them by his Judgments to break of ſinne, but they will not hear the voice of Gods Rodd, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. <hi>verſe</hi> 3. they refuſe to receive Correction; when once it is thus with a people, God will pack up and be gon from them, 7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.14. <hi>ver. Therefore will I doe to this Houſe which is called b my Name, as I did to</hi> Shilo; why what did God do to <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo?</hi> when he left the tokens of his wrath there at <hi>Shilo,</hi> the Prieſt was ſlain, the Arke taken Priſoner, all the ſigns of Gods preſence were removed, and we never read that the Arke retuned to <hi>Shilo</hi> any more. Oh dreadful! hath not the Lord blown the Trumpet in our
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30535:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> ears? hath not be called to us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, but we hate to be reformed, we turn a deaf ear to God; let <hi>England,</hi> let <hi>London,</hi> take heed it be not with it, as once with <hi>Shilo</hi> that God does not make the Viſion ceaſe, and bring a Famine of the word in theſe our days, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. <hi>verſe</hi> 23. pray obſerve, 24.30. ſaith God, <hi>verſe</hi> 23. I <hi>will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you yet ſeven times more, for your ſinnes</hi> I <hi>will make you lie waſte, and</hi> I <hi>will bring your Sanctuary into deſolation,</hi> that is the firſt thing: if you would prevent a Goſpel Famine, I beſeech you beloved take heede of thoſe ſinnes which you have ſeen have brought a Famine of Gods Word upon a Land.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If you would prevent a Famine of the Goſpel, let us beſiege the Throne of Grace by earneſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; Oh pray to God, you that can pray, pray, that the Lord would not depart from you, that he would not make the Viſion ceaſe, that he would not turne the Songs of our Temple in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Howleing, Oh lay hold upon Chriſt by importunitie you read of thoſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30535:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the Goſpel, when Chriſt made as if he was going away, the Text ſaith, they did conſtrain his to ſtay with them, <hi>Luke</hi> 24. Verſe 29. Is not the Lord upon the Thraſhal of his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as if he was ready to take his wings and flye from us? Oh let us by hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prayer lye at his Feet, and if it be poſſible, conſtraine him yet to ſtay with <hi>England;</hi> ſtay Lord, rather any Judgement than this! rather lay a ſtroake upon my body or Eſtate, but doe not bring a Famine of the Word of God; and if we would prevaile with the Lord, uſe Arguments in prayer when we come to God for the poor Goſpel of <hi>England:</hi> Lord haſt thou never a Remnant left among us, a People that love thee, and fears thee, that hangs about thee, that will not let thee goe? Oh deſtroy not the cluſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is not there a bleſſing in it? Oh wilt thou be gone from us, art not thou our Father, will the Father take away Bread from his Children? Lord, will not the Enemie inſult to ſee thee leaving thy Temple, where thou haſt put thy Name? wilt thou make the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30535:22"/> hearts of thy people ſadde, and wilt thou rejoyce thine Enemies? Oh Lord, haſt thou not given Bond, and is there better. Security? haſt thou not promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed under thy Hand and Seale thou wilt give us Paſtors after thine own heart to feed us with Knowledge? Lord, thou wilt never Forfeit thy Bond. It is true, we are an unworthy Nation, not worthy to be Beloved; Oh but canſt not thou make us fit for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie? canſt not thou give us Repentance as well as Deliverance? Nay Lord, let us farther preſs thee, is not thy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour concerned in all this? we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by thy Name, leave us not; thus ſhould we uſe Arguments and follow God by prayer, and ſurely the Lord will not depart from us. Prayer, it makes a ſweet ſound in Gods Ear, and he will not goe away, where he hears this Muſick, Againe,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Would we prevent a Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Famine (which we have cauſe to fear) let us this day turne to God and break off our ſinnes by righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. Verſe 3. Amend your
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30535:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> wayes and your doings, it is a vain thing to pray unleſs you reform, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend your wayes and your doings: What ſhould God continue his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel for to an impenitent ſinnefull Land, that are reſolved they will ſinne; who will lay out coſt upon ground that brings forth nothing but Briars? who will power Roſe-water upon a Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill? Would we prevent a Goſpel Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, let us breake up the Follow ground of our hearts by Repentance. I will ſay but this, if we Reforme not, we can expect to ſee no good dayes more, God will un-People us, he will un-Church us ere he hath done; Oh bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter looſe the Sunne in the Firmament, than that the Goſpel Sunne ſhould be Eclipſed in our Horiſon: who would deſire to live when the Arke of God is gone? what good Chriſtian can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare weeping at the Funeral of the Goſpel? that is the firſt exhortation; let us labour to prevent the coming of Gods Famine upon us, as we would prevent Fire, and Plague, ſo labour to prevent this Soul Famine.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:30535:23"/>
            <p>Seccond <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> of Exhortation is this, if a Famine of the Word be ſo ſad as you have heard, let us doe what we can to keep God ſtill amongſt us and his Goſpel. You will ſay how ſhall we keep the Goſpel, it is a bleſſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne to keep the Goſpel? I will name three or four things, and I have done.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Entertain the Goſpel into your houſes, that is one way to keep it; <hi>Obadiah</hi> he entertained the Ark, and his houſe was bleſſed for the Ark ſake; if you cannot have the Goſpel in poblick, as you uſe to have with purity and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, get it into your houſes; I am ſure of this, you can never put your houſes to better uſe, then to entertain Chriſt and his Goſpel; I beſeech you let it not be ſaid, that the Goſpel is put to ſeek its lodging; does not this Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel bring Salvation? Oh how glad ſhould you be to have Salvation come to your Houſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Would you keep the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30535:23"/> among you? Improve it the beſt way, I know ſtill to enjoy the Goſpel, is to improve it, lay up a ſtock of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, let the word of Chriſt dwell richly in you, <hi>coll.</hi> 3. Verſe 16. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Word not only into your heads, but into your hearts, get good by the word Preached, while the Manna falls gather Manna, the beſt way to enjoye the Goſpel is to improve it, God will not take away the Breſt, ſo long as Faith draws the breſt. And then,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Priſe the Goſpel and that is the way to keep it, the Ordinances of God are the moſt ſignal bleſſings, they are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then Gold &amp; Silver, they are the food of your ſouls, they ſtrengthen faith, they increaſe joy; theſe are the Conduits that holds the Water of Life, that ſoul that before was dry like <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod being planted near theſe waters of the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, have flouriſhed, have brought forth Buds and Almonds, and therefore priſe the Ordinances. Beloved here we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, if ever we enjoy Chriſt upon earth, it is here; if ever we ſee his face, it is through this Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:30535:24"/> Gods Ordinances are like the place of the Mercy Seat, where the Lord did ſpeak from heaven to his People; oh then priſe theſe Goſpel bleſſings, and that is the way yet to keep them among you.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, If you would keep the Goſpel with you, adorne the Goſpel, you that are here preſent, you do all profeſs the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, that is not enough, unleſſe you adorn the Goſpel, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27. Let your Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation be as becomes the Goſpel; but when do we adorn the Goſpel? I anſwer, when we live according to the rule of the Goſpel in ſobriety and ſanctity, Oh that is to adorn it: when we walk according to the rule of it in ſobriety and ſanctity, we adorn the Goſpel; when we walk as the Members of Chriſt, and as thoſe that are acted by his Spirit, we adorn the Goſpel; when we ſhine forth in a kind of Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal brightneſſe, and live ſo holy as if we had ſeen the Lord, this is to adorne the Goſpel, and this is the beſt way I know to have the Goſpel intailed upon us, and upon our poſterity after us.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30535:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
